So tonight we're going to be diving into
US foreign policy under Donald Trump
from the al-Qaeda takeover in Syria. Uh
Israel Palestine, also what is going on
with Russia and the uh trying to end the
war with Ukraine. And we're going to be
talking about the question that sparks
endless debate. Can we or should we get
rid of the CIA? To help navigate this
minefield of geopolitics, we're speaking
with someone who knows the CIA inside
and out. former CIA officer and
whistleblower John Kuryaku. John spent
14 years in the CIA, specializing in
counterterrorism and leading high-risk
operations, including a pivotal role in
capturing Abu Zuba, who was once
believed to be al-Qaeda's third in
command. But John's legacy didn't stop
there. In 2007, during an explosive
interview with ABC News, he revealed
that Zubeta had been tortured by US
operatives, making him one of the first
insiders to confirm America's use of
torture post 911. But instead of being
celebrated for exposing this dark
chapter, John was vilified and
ultimately sent to prison for two years.
He's the only person to have served time
in connection with the US torture
program post 911, not for committing
torture, but for blowing the whistle on
it. John has gone on to lend his
insights, hosting numerous shows,
including Political Misfits and Loud and
Clear on Sputnik Radio, The
Whistleblowers on RT, and now he has a
new show called CIA Declassified on
Unified TV, where he delves into covert
operations and controversial practices
of the CIA, offering viewers and
insiders perspective on the AY's
clandestine activities. It's really
great to have John joining us again on
the show. This will be, I think, his
third or fourth time being here, which
is always so great to talk to him. John,
welcome to the show. Thank you so much
for being here.
>> Thank you, Kim. It's good to see you
again.
>> Good to see you. Oh, there's so much
going on in the world. I can't wait to
pick your brain on everything that's
going on with this new administration.
>> Yeah.
>> Where should we start with the world?
>> Oh my god. Um, let's start with Syria
actually with with what happened during
the Biden administration, you know,
recently with Syria, the fall of Assad,
um, with, uh, al-Qaeda and, you know,
al-Qaeda essentially taking over the
country. Um, what
>> Yeah, you're not overstating it.
>> Oh, boy.
>> You know, wow. Where do you even start
with this with this Syria issue? This
was a major victory for Turkey and for
Israel and to a lesser extent for the
United States, but but we don't really
get a whole lot out of it. But, you
know, the Turks could not have moved at
a more perfect time. This fit right into
the Israeli playbook, which then leads
me to conclude that uh they were in
cahoots on it. Uh it's a serious setback
for the Russians and for the Iranians to
the point where it could it could lead
to um to domestic problems in Iran
because people are furious that the
Iranian government apparently did
nothing to protect the Assad government.
Uh the Israelis immediately moved in and
took a little strip along the border and
have said that they have no intention of
getting out. And then all of a sudden
al-Qaeda's in charge of the country. And
not only is al-Qaeda in charge of Syria
now, but this is the al-Qaeda faction
that is supported by the CIA. It was
opposed by the Pentagon, but supported
by the CIA, financed and armed by the
CIA. And then the State Department sent
a high level delegation led by Assistant
Secretary of State Barbara Leaf, an old
colleague of mine, to meet with the new
head of this this faction that controls
the Syrian government, and to announce
that the United States was lifting its
$10 million bounty that had been placed
on his head. So, if that isn't Bizarro
World, I don't know what is.
I mean, it's just such a why why were we
supporting this guy? I mean, this this
is I mean, this guy fought against
American troops, right? I mean, this guy
killed Americans. Um I mean, we went and
we were fighting al-Qaeda and now
>> and now we're supporting them. I mean,
what do you think a lot of people and
you know, I I've suspected of course
that Israel really had it was all
Israel. Whatever Israel wanted when it
came to Syria is kind of what we just
kind of went with whatever they wanted
when it came to
>> and they got it.
>> Yes.
>> And they Right. And so how why are we
putting their interests ahead of I mean
look a lot of us don't agree with the
war in Iraq. Right. We never should have
gone in. There was all of that. Um but
nonetheless we did go in. These guys
fought. I mean they were I guess it's
kind of complicated now looking back
like do do we say they were freedom
fighters or were they terrorists? like
which what what were they? I mean, what
would you say they are?
>> And that and that's a thin line. I would
say they were terrorists because look,
this this Syrian
it's um it's it's the latest the newest
iteration of the Nusra front which had
been called al-Qaeda and it broke off
from from ISIS, right? because it wanted
to focus specifically on Syria rather
than on this this giant caliphate that
uh that uh the Islamic Front or ISIS uh
had initially set out to establish. So
the CIA began supporting it while the
Pentagon was supporting a different
organization that was I I saw it
described in the New York Times recently
as as a a group of unaffiliated rebels.
It's all nonsensical.
But the truth of the matter is actually,
you know what? I'm going to simplify
this. I'm going to boil it down to
something that that my oldest son told
me when he was 9 years old. When when my
oldest son was nine and his brother was
six, I took them to a WWE professional
wrestling match in Madison Square
Garden. And these guys are breaking
chairs over their heads and tables and
throwing each other out of the ring. And
I said to my son, I don't think I get
it. Which one is the good guy? And he
said, 'Well, that's just it, Dad. There
is no good guy. That's Syria today.
There's no good guy. So, what you do is
you ally yourself with the the group
that you think is the least of the bad
guys.
>> Yeah. And I if if these al-Qaeda people
are people that are going to lay down
their arms visav the United States,
they're going to work closely with the
government of Turkey, they're going to
allow an Israeli occupation of their
southwestern border, the United States
can live with that. Now, one of the
reasons why I think that this is so
wrong and so shortsighted, Kim, is you
don't have to like Bashar al-Assad. You
don't have to like his politics, but
Bashar al-Assad is uh is a a Shia Muslim
in a majority Muslim country. He's an
Alawi, which is a minority sect within
Shiism.
And because the Aloise are a minority of
a minority, they have always had respect
for other religious minorities. So, you
know, I've been to to church in in an
Orthodox cathedral in Damascus. Damascus
has one of the oldest continuously
operating synagogues in the world. There
are Christians and Jews that serve in
the Syrian government, that serve in the
parliament, that serve in the cabinet.
There are women that serve in the
parliament and cabinet. And women don't
have to cover themselves.
His his personal politics aside, for
many years it was Bashar Assad who was
standing between the Christian community
in Syria and complete annihilation.
Do you trust Christians to to live under
the thumb of al-Qaeda?
Do you believe the State Department when
it says, "Oh, don't worry about
al-Qaeda. They're going to respect all
faiths." Come on. You know, as the old
saying goes, I was I was born during the
day, but not yesterday. And that's
really what it comes down to.
>> Why is Israel being so shortsighted on
this? Also, I mean, I understand that
their whole what they were trying to do
was was eradicate the axis of evil,
right? That that's what they were kind
of trying to to go after. And they
wanted to dismantle anything that was
Iranianbacked.
Um, but but al-Qaeda, I I just don't
they're not going to be friends. I mean,
they're not I don't see where this I
don't see if this is going to be like,
oh, they're going to just let the
Israelis live there side by side without
any problems. I mean, this just seems
short short-sighted on their part as
well.
>> Yeah, the Israelis get two things out of
this. Uh, number one, Hezbollah is is no
longer uh helping to prop up the Assad
government, and the Iranians are no
longer uh sending arms uh to the Assad
government. That's number one. Number
two, the Israelis always win in Syria
when there's chaos. The Israelis want
Syrians to to kill each other and to
fight each other and for various
factions to control different parts of
the country. And the best part of it for
the for the Israelis is that the United
States occupies that small part of Syria
where oil is produced. And the oil is
going to Turkey. It's not going to Iran.
It's not going to to Hezbollah. It's not
being uh shipped uh south through Jordan
and over to uh to Yemen. So the the
Israelis come out ahead when there's
chaos. They've decapitated Hezbollah.
The Iranians have gone home with their
tails between their legs. And so the
Israelis just chuck that up as a win.
>> Again, a short-sighted win. I mean, how
long can you have your neighbors be in
chaos? I mean, that's not sustainable.
>> Yeah, you're you're exactly right. And I
I've long said that the devil you know
is better than the devil you don't. You
know, there have long been or there had
been long uh uh secret talks between the
Israeli government and the Syrians.
That's why there were never border
clashes because they came to an
agreement in 2004 not to fight over the
border. And if you know that you can
deal with Bashar al-Assad,
you can handle the the Iranians, you can
handle Hezbollah, you can ask the
Americans to weigh in or ask the Turks
to weigh in or ask even the Iraqis to
weigh in. And uh the Israelis decided
that
>> that they were better with chaos. I
think it's very short-sighted.
>> Yeah, really shortsighted. What do you
think is going to happen to that region
of the world? I mean with um
yeah I mean what what do you think long
let's talk long term like long term so
ju not even just the Trump
administration these next four years
what he chooses to do but I mean really
long term what's going to happen over
there
>> I think that Syria is now a failed state
>> um akin to Libya or Somalia or Yemen um
over the medium to long term the only
way that they can dig their way out of
this is if the Gulf states come through
for them in a very big way with money.
The the Saudi government was more
dedicated to the overthrow of Bashar
al-Assad than pretty much any other
country on the planet except maybe
Israel. Um and now they have that.
>> Yeah. Why?
>> Because he was Shia.
>> He was Shia and close to the Iranians
and and Iran is Saudi Arabia's arch
enemy. And so they always wanted him out
and now he's out. So somebody has to
build an airport, water treatment
facilities, oil refineries, hospitals,
schools, decent roads. The country is
devastated. As I said, it's it's a
failed state. It looks like like
Somalia. Now, if the if the the Saudis
come through, the Amiradis and the
Gutteries over the long term, maybe they
can turn Syria into something that
perhaps someday might look like, let's
say, Tunisia.
>> I think that would be the best case
scenario.
>> Yeah. What do you think is the
long-term? What's going to happen to
Israel? I mean, this is just, you know,
also just seems really unsustainable the
way that they
>> unsustainable.
>> Yeah. I mean, what do you think's going
to happen?
>> You know, the Israeli policy, let's just
call a spade a spade here. The Israeli
policy is to kill everybody,
>> and that's not that's not a policy. You
can't kill everybody. There there was
something that Donald Trump said several
weeks ago that that really frightened
me. He said that um that Gaza could be
the next Monaco. No, Gaza can be better
than Monaco.
Yeah, that's great. But he meant without
any Palestinians, and that's a
non-starter.
>> You know, within 24 hours, Kim, of of
the ceasefire between Hamas and Israel,
the Israelis launched a major offensive
in the West Bank.
>> Well, of course they did. I think
everybody in the world expected them to
to move into the West Bank because the
policy is to is to either kill or throw
out every Palestinian. And again, that
is unsustainable. You just can't it it
can't work. It won't work. I'm sure that
you've been to Israel. I was there twice
last year and I there's no other country
on earth like Israel where you have the
first world and the third world living
side by side separated only by high
walls and barbed wire and that's not a
sustainable model for a state.
>> No, no. I mean now they're talking about
moving all of the gazins to Indonesia. I
mean that's what they're like. Oh, give
them one of the 17,000 islands of
Indonesia. You know, they can have one
of those and we'll just move them there.
And that's what they're talking about.
>> You know, they used to That's right. And
they used to talk in the 1980s, they
used to talk about well, along the
border of Saudi Arabia and Iraq, there
was this diamond that was called um uh
the disputed territory, right? That was
it. The disputed territory. And it was a
couple of hundred square miles, very,
very small. Um there was talk about just
naming that Palestine and moving them
all there. The thing is is nothing can
live there. I mean, even insects don't
live there. It's just dust. It has no
water. It has no oil. It has no trees,
no shrubs, no shade, no nothing. And
then the Iraqis and the Saudis came to a
border agreement and that idea went
away. But this idea of just picking up
an entire people and moving them, it's
unprecedented really in the history of
the world and it's just not tenable.
>> Yeah.
>> May I add something too? May I add
something? Yeah. part part of the part
of the problem, a very big part of the
problem is that the the Israeli
government in in recent times, like in
the last 20 years, let's say, has moved
so far to the right that that is also
untenable. And it's moved that far to
the right because of the influx of
refugees and immigrants from Russia,
Ukraine, and the United States.
those Jews coming from from those three
countries
have been have been conservative to a
point that the Israeli populace had
never seen before. Long gone are the
days are the days when German Jews,
Polish Jews, French Jews moved to uh
Palestine and then and then Israel after
and had a socialist government all sang
Kumbaya around the campfire. Those days
are gone. these Russians and Ukrainians
that run the country now will stop at
nothing short of pushing every
Palestinian out.
>> What is it about that part of the world,
Ukraine, uh in particular, if you look
at that the map, you know, I'm not I'm
not just calling out Ukrainians. I'm
just saying that that area of the world,
what is it about that part of the world
that creates such radical radical
fanatics? I mean when you look at the
history of that region and who came from
there, right? The Austria, Hungary,
Ukraine, right? You got Hitler came from
that area. Ben came from that area. Uh
you have the early the earliest Zionists
that were the big terrorists were from
that area and immigrating down to Israel
and they're all from that area.
>> What is it about that area that brings
>> hyper nationalistic
>> racist, you know, leaders?
You're talking about going back even as
far as 100, 110 years. Remember, the
Ukrainians threw flowers at Nazi troops
when they entered the Soviet Union
>> in 1940. Flowers. They threw flowers at
them. And you're right, Bandera uh was a
a Nazi who was perfectly happy to march
in lock step with German Nazis. You
know, it's it's the culture there.
Scholars will tell you that it was a
reaction against Bolecheism and that
very well may be true because the
Bolsheviks brought, you know, famine
and, you know, pestilence and war. But
come on, people, it was a century ago.
It's time to move on.
>> Yeah.
>> Otherwise, I I can't explain it.
>> I I just I you know, and when we do look
back at history, and I Yeah. looking
back a hundred or so years, I mean, this
is where kind of the worst of the worst
come from that region of the world. And
it it's almost like and and then they
spread out like I said they were the
earliest Zionists that were the
terrorists that went to Israel and
created the nation you know precursors
to the creation of Israel
>> blew up the King David hotel
>> right I mean that's they were from that
area they were all from that area and
there's something about and this is what
you know when people talk about the
Russia Ukraine war they talk about u you
know Putin saying we got to denazify the
area or whatever and we and then we see
very radical Nazilike mentality inside
of Ukraine.
you know, still very much prevalent,
still celebrated.
>> Um, I mean, Germany has always had a a
beef with Austria for not doing more to
acknowledge their role in the Holocaust.
And, you know, they're like, "You guys
need a little bit more, but you
>> Ukraine did nothing."
>> Even today, nothing. Nothing. Even
today, just as an aside, Austria has the
smallest percentage of Jews in Europe
and the highest percentage of people who
blame their problems on Jews. I mean
that's
>> Yeah,
>> that's fascism.
>> Yeah. Right. And they never rooted it
out. So Germany says to Austria, "You
need to do more to root it out. You guys
haven't done enough." Well, Ukraine did
nothing to root out their Nazi past.
They did absolutely nothing. And it
seems like that part of the world. Uh
maybe maybe that is the issue. Like
they've there's just never been a
concerted effort to attack that hyper
nationalistic. I mean, it just seems
like that's the birthplace of
nationalism. When I look back at the era
that that created the early Zionists and
Nazi, you know, the bander, like that
whole, it just seems like there was a
growing mentality amongst the people
that's that spread a little bit and it
was just this hyper nationalist, a home
for just our kind, you know, we wanted
>> and and look at it this way. Oh, yeah. I
think you're I think you're 100% right.
And look at it this way.
Why try to change that when the United
States says in 1945, "Hey, all you
Nazis, we're happy to take you guys. Uh,
listen, the doctors, the engineers, the
rocket scientists, we have this thing
called Operation Paperclip, come on in.
We're going to take all of you." And
then the Israelis say, "Oh, you're
you're Jewish, but still kind of Nazi.
That's okay. We can work with that. Come
on to Israel. So long as you're Jewish,
we don't care what kind of politics you
have. And then here we are just self
flagagillating and wondering how in the
world we got ourselves in this position.
>> Yeah. Well, that's and that kind of
brings us back to Syria and al-Qaeda,
right? I mean, it's like
here we, you know, here we are. History
once again, you know, we just keep
propping up and funding and and
scratching the back of people that
ultimately are radical. and later on
this is just going to hurt us. I mean I
just don't understand.
>> So with Syria in regards to Syria,
>> we don't I mean what B so you're saying
the United States has no benefit out of
I mean what what didn't matter? What did
it matter to us anyway if Assad was in
power or if al-Qaeda is in power? But it
does seem like, you know, our so-called
greatest ally for our so-called greatest
ally to put in power, the group that we
have been telling all the American
people, this is why we were going to war
in the Middle East, the war on terror,
that we had to fight al-Qaeda, that
al-Qaeda attacked us. I mean, we're the
only country that has triggered an
article 5 with NATO and that was 911. We
blame it on al-Qaeda,
>> right? We say al-Qaeda did this to us
and now we're cheering on at the behest
of Israel al-Qaeda taking over Syria and
we're like I guess we'll just shake
hands and call it you know let bygones
be bygones. I mean I don't understand
>> it's it what has happened that has
allowed
>> it does it
>> defies belief. Listen, I listen, I'm I'm
as I'm as willing as the next guy to to
recognize changes around the world, but
this isn't this isn't a change that's
worthy of our support. It's al-Qaeda for
heaven's sake. They can pick whatever
name they want. But do we really think
that we want to be in business with
al-Qaeda? What I hope has happened here
is that, you know, like my son when he
was 9 years old, he recognized that
there was no good guy. He recognized he
recognized that he didn't have an
interest in who the winner was anyway so
long as there was a good fight. And
perhaps the White House and the State
Department backed off and just decided
we're going to let the Turks and the
Israelis figure this out because they're
the ones that have the more immediate um
interests uh in who leads Syria. We
really don't care who leads Syria. We're
happy with the fact that the Russians
are pushed out, with the fact that the
Iranians have been pushed out, and with
the fact that that the Israelis
essentially have decapitated Hezbollah.
Hisbala as a fighting force no longer
exists. It's going to take years to
rebuild. And so, if the Turks want
al-Qaeda and the Israelis are cool with
al-Qaeda,
then what do we care? We're just going
to let them go with al-Qaeda. I I will
say I was disturbed with this with this
um announcement a couple of weeks ago
that we're going to reopen the American
embassy in Damascus. That's a little bit
too much dog on recognition of al-Qaeda
for my taste,
>> right?
>> You know, and it's like all the
conspiracies around 911. I know that a
lot of um you know there's a lot of
blame being pointed at like Israel or
something, but now I'm like I don't
know. I think al-Qaeda did it. I think
that this goes to show al-Qaeda totally
did it and they were playing the long
game. They were like, "Guys, 25 years
from now, we'll have our own country.
Just wait. You know, let's do this, and
I swear to you, it'll play out. In 25
years, we'll have a country."
>> And here they are.
>> Crazier things that happen.
>> That's their reward for all for for
that. I mean, it's
>> so so insane. Um,
>> I went to college with this.
>> Yeah. Go ahead.
>> No, no, no. Go ahead.
>> No. Well, I just wanted to move on to
Trump and his foreign policy in the
Middle East. I you know there's
it's hard to read the guy mixed messages
right lots of mixed messages coming from
him.
>> What do you think of mixed messages?
>> Yeah. Yeah. What do you you know he had
a lot of big donors $und00 million from
Miriam Add. He had a lot of other big
Jewish Zionist and Christian Zionist
donors um who really want to see
>> uh you know the Palestinians driven out
of Israel or you know they they want to
see Israel just as a one big Jewish
nation. What do you think is but then he
says you know on his first day in office
when he was asked um do you think the
ceasefire will hold the first thing out
of his mouth was probably not it's not
our war and then he says it's not our
war. Um, what do you think he's What do
you think he's going to do in regards to
Israel? Are we going to still fund them,
give them all the bombs they want, and
continue on, or what do you think
Trump's going to do? I know it's
probably hard to guess because he is so
murial, but what do you think?
>> He is very murial and and very
unpredictable.
Um, but you know what? I think I like
that right now because Joe Biden was
very predictable and there was never any
chance that Joe Joe Biden was going to
stand up against Israeli genocide
against the Palestinian people. Joe
Biden was in up to his neck in Israel's
uh war crimes uh and and attacks against
civilians in Gaza and in the West Bank
for that matter. So to think that that
Joe Biden was somehow this man of peace
who was gonna figure out the Middle East
uh fight, it was it was a fool's errand.
I was pleasantly surprised by two
things. I was pleasantly surprised by
the fact that that Donald Trump said
that it was likely that the ceasefire
would not hold and he criticized Israeli
war crimes. That's the first time that's
first time since George HW Bush that a
president has criticized Israel in a
meaningful way.
>> Yeah. Um, and second,
you know, he takes a lot of heat for
nepotism, of course, and deservedly so
in many cases, but his appointment of
Tiffany Trump's father-in-law, who is a
Greek Orthodox of Lebanese origin, a
billionaire named Bros, as the special
as his special envoy for for middle for
the Middle East, excuse me. Mhm.
>> I thought was actually an inspired
choice for a couple of reasons. The
Saudis
always always insist that the US
ambassador be a political appointee, not
a diplomat, because they want somebody
who has direct access to the president.
Well, who better to have direct access
to the president than his kmbaro?
There's not an English word for that.
That's the Greek word, but you know,
kari and you know what I mean. Um,
>> yeah. Yeah, this guy's family-in-law.
>> This guy's family. All he has to do is
pick up the telephone and say, "Hey, you
know, this is what we need to do in the
Middle East." Um, the fact that he's
that he's not Jewish and not a not a an
unrelated businessman, I think, is
actually very positive. And so I'm kind
of excited to see what initiatives might
be uh uh begun in the Middle East,
whether there is a plan for Palestine,
whether there is a plan to smack the
Israelis down a peg or two, especially
as they move into the West Bank. I think
we ought to give the Trump foreign
policy team, whether it's at the White
House or the State Department, the
benefit of the doubt for the first, you
know, six or 12 months and see where it
goes. Yeah.
Yeah. It's certainly going to be
interesting. I do think that Trump has,
you know, one thing I noticed when he
was when he was asked that question
about the ceasefire. Um, and he said,
well, I mean, the place is destroy, you
know, he he said the place was
destroyed. You know, the pictures of the
place, it looks terrible. And the way he
says it, the look on his face is not the
way like Netanyahu's face would look,
you know, like like gloating, like look
what we've done, you know? He looked he
looked like have you seen the place? You
know, it's it looks you know his the
look on his face was shocked.
>> And I also think he has a real genu I
think he genuinely has a real soft spot
for children. I think he genuinely
>> does not like to see dead babies. And I
think that
>> I think that's exactly right.
>> That really has I think he's like this
has to stop.
He's reading the same news that we're
reading that there are two million
people on the move in in the biggest
mass refugee migration since the the end
of the Second World War. This is an area
of 2 million people with not a single
working hospital.
There's not enough food. There's not
enough water. There are no medical
supplies. And there's no plan either by
the Israelis or the Americans or you
know NATO or whomever the European Union
to do anything meaningful about it. And
the guy's a human being. He's not bound
to policy the way the way Democrats and
Republicans who happen to be
professional politicians are bound. And
so, like I say, I I I'm willing to give
him the benefit of the doubt that maybe
as an outsider looking in, he can
actually come up with a plan.
>> Yeah.
>> I hope.
>> Yeah. Let's hope. Let's hope. Uh
certainly. I mean, he's difficult to
read because he does like to talk tough
and I that moves me to Russia. Um he
loves to talk tough. He likes to say,
"Do you better come to the table and
talk to me or else, right?" That's kind
of seems to be
>> Yeah, it seems to be his, you know, that
that's how he I guess it's the art of
the deal. I, you know, just bully them
to the table and then you start to
negotiate. Uh, so he kind of made some
comments towards Hamas, like, "Oh, it's
going to be terrible." And I think he
probably said the same thing to Israel,
like, "Come to the table or I'm cutting
you off." You know, and what we're
seeing now is he's saying to the
Russians, um he just recently said to
the Russians, "Come to the table or
we're going to sanction the hell out of
you and you're going to have economic
destruction hit your country like never
foreseen." Which I Yes.
>> I mean, do you think now I see how that
might work with the Palestinians and the
Israelis because you've got some serious
leverage there with you could cut off
the Israelis from weapons. You really
could do that. And the Palestinians are
being destroyed. So, they're obviously
already uh very frightened with what's
going on for them. But Russia and
Ukraine, um, can you play, do you think
that he can play that same game with
Putin
>> and have Putin actually say, "Oh, I'm
shaking in my boots. Hold on. Let me get
to the negotiation table." I mean, do
you think that's going to work?
>> Well, I I'll give you a two-part answer.
I think that in the in the near term, it
could work for a while, so long as he
can um as so long as he can control
Republican politicians on Capitol Hill.
The only leverage really that he has
over Russia is his ability to continue
supplying Ukraine with arms. We know
that the Republican party is pretty
solidly opposed to continuing to supply
Ukrainians. Um
>> yeah,
>> I'm going to go out on a limb and say
that I think that what world leaders
were talking about, you know, three
years ago, uh is what is going to come
to pass. and that is that
that the end of this war is going to be
the Russians keeping the Donbass and
Crimea.
The Ukrainians jumping up and down and
saying we win, we win the war, even
though they didn't.
>> Um, Ukraine will not become a part of
NATO, but it will become a part of the
European Union. And uh, and that's going
to be the end of it. These two countries
can't bleed each other forever. There's
there's an end point and there are only
so many troops that the North Koreans
are going to be able to send in. And by
all accounts, Russian casualties are
high, right? Russian morale is low.
Ukrainian morale is low, too. But if
you've got this neverending spot of
money and arms and weapons systems, you
can keep that up for quite a while. But
I think this is what's going to happen.
I think that that Trump is going to
force the two sides into talks. Even if
they're indirect talks, he'll probably
negotiate something on the QT with with
Putin. The Russians will get to keep the
the Russians speaking areas that they
now control and Crimea.
Everybody declares victory and they go
home.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. I only see Putin going to the
table because he wants to go to the
table. He wants to go to the negotiation
table. I don't know if this whole like
>> Exactly. Right.
>> Oh, we're going to crush you if you if
you don't. I don't think that's going to
work. I don't think that's why he comes
to the table. He's like, I just want to
have this conversation.
I think it's on his terms.
>> Um,
>> and may I add something on that point,
too?
>> Yeah.
>> I think I think you raised a very
important point here. Uh, and and that's
the issue of sanctions. These sanctions
are practically unilateral. I mean, it's
just us in the European Union. But if
the Chinese are ignoring them and the
Indians are ignoring them and they just
signed this new big deal with the the
Iranians that was 20 years in the
making, the Russians can live perfectly
well without the United States and the
European Union. If we don't want to buy
Russian gas or the Europeans don't want
to buy Russian gas, the Chinese and the
Indians are very happy to buy Russian
gas. I happened to go to Hong Kong uh
last spring on a business trip and I was
surprised that so many places don't take
Visa and Mastercard. They have this
thing called it's like Panda Card I
think is what it was called. And uh a
Chinese contact explained to me, "Oh
yeah, we use Panda Card. It's just the
same as Visa or Mastercard, but it the
transactions not routed through New
York. So in the event that the United
States puts sanctions on China, now the
Chinese don't care. They don't use Visa
and Mastercard. They don't use the
American banking system. Well, the
Russians now have adopted the same
program where we can put we can put
sanctions on Russia from now till, you
know, the end times. It's not going to
make any difference. They couldn't live
without us. And it's because we've
overplayed our sanctions hand over the
years. I remember even when I was still
at the CIA, we were threatening the
Iranians with sanctions. And I said to a
colleague, "How many more sanctions
could there possibly be? We've been
sanctioning them since 1979, and we're
still coming up with new sanctions. That
doesn't make any sense."
>> Well, the Russians have learned that
lesson, too.
>> Yeah.
Yeah. I think it'll be good to see that
one. And I know that during the um one
of his meetings, you know, Trump just
kind of rattles stuff off and I think he
had mentioned the casualty numbers for
Ukraine and Russia and the casualty
numbers were something like
>> 600,000 or 700,000 on Ukraine side and
800,000 on the Russian side. To be clear
though, I think when we say casualty, we
mean injury and death, right? That's not
just
>> correct. Correct. And I think the actual
numbers for both of them are half that.
I think he exaggerated but but his his
basic point that this has been a
catastrophic conflict is true.
>> Mhm.
>> How many of those do you think are
death?
>> Oh, I'm I'm going to say a quarter.
If you look at previous conflicts,
deaths have been about a quarter. And
you know, in in places like Afghanistan
and Iraq, we were we were lucky because
our um battlefield medicine is so much
more sophisticated than other countries
when it comes to traumatic brain
injuries where where those soldiers
would have died during the Vietnam War
or even into the 1980s, they're able to
be saved now even though they have, you
know, lifelong uh traumatic brain
injuries. The Ukrainians and the
Russians don't have that kind of of
luxury, that kind of advanced medicine
on the battlefield and a lot of those
soldiers die.
>> Yeah. Hopefully that one ends um that
conflict. Hopefully we don't get into
anymore.
>> Yeah. Trying to think where else in the
world are we are we um having issues
like there's uh I mean Trump is talking
a lot about purchasing you know
Greenland.
>> Yeah. Did you see there was a
>> spree?
>> Oh yeah, he is. And he and he used the
word expansion which scared the
daylights out of the Panameanians.
>> And then uh a a Danish member of
parliament uh said f you.
>> Yeah.
>> F you. He said Greenland's not for sale.
Listen, we already have military bases
in Greenland anyway. So, I think he's,
you know, I I have a friend who used to
be the the chairman of the Republican uh
party in Texas, and he told me something
last weekend that just made me laugh,
and he said, "Trump doesn't have any
designs on on Greenland." Trump likes to
throw these grenades into the middle of
the room because it distracts the media
from issues that are more important to
him, like confirmation fights, for
example, or his tax bill. let people
spend their time or waste their time
arguing about Greenland and the Panama
Canal while he gets this tax bill
passed.
>> Yeah. And the Gulf of America.
>> That's true. The Gulf of America. He
signed Yeah. He signed and Mount
McKinley. He signed executive orders on
the first Listen, nobody nobody's going
to call it the Gulf of America. I had to
chuckle. Yeah. When I was at the CIA, um
I used to complain that that analysts
who didn't speak Arabic would use the
full formal name of um of countries and
cities. Like for example,
uh uh Bahrain, everybody knows the
country Bahrain. In Arabic, it's
actually al Bahrain. Kuwait is al
Kuwait. The city of Doha in ger is adoha
or al-bas in southern Iraq. Nobody says
that. Only CIA analysts say that because
it's in the the official gazette, right?
>> Um uh
so then because they don't speak Arabic
and they don't hear Arabs saying it,
they they use these these antiquated
formal names. Well,
>> yeah,
>> the internationally recognized name of
the Gulf of Mexico is the Gulf of
Mexico. And it doesn't matter how many
executive orders Donald Trump signs,
it's not going to be the Gulf of
America. It's gonna be the Gulf of
Mexico forever,
>> right?
Let's talk about the CIA. Um, we've got
a new appointed director, John
Ratcliffe. What does a director of CIA
actually do? I mean, what's the
significance when you get a new director
in there?
>> Yeah, it's a big deal. It's not as big a
deal as it used to be um before the
creation of the Office of the Director
of National Intelligence. Um, but it's
it's a big deal. You know, let let me
explain the the differences between CIA
director and the DNI. The DNI, director
of national intelligence, is the nominal
head of all 18 intelligence agencies
that we have in government. And I say
nominal head because really what the DNI
controls is the budget and the
president's daily brief. That's it.
Nobody goes to the DNI to say, "Hey, let
me tell you about this uh idea for a
covert action plan that we have, or
we're going to go over here and do this,
or we're going to open a secret base
over here." The DNI isn't even cleared
for some of that information. All the
DNI does is the budget and the
president's daily brief. Um,
>> where do they get the brief? I mean,
they have to get the brief from the
agencies, right?
>> From the from the CI. the the yeah the
PDB used to be a CIA only publication
only and now it's been opened up to the
State Department's Bureau of
Intelligence and Research and to DIA. So
their their analysts are able to
contribute articles and because the the
PDB staff, the editors now sit under the
ODNI,
they are the ones that accept and reject
and edit whatever they think the
president needs to see the next morning
at 0700. So that that's nice, but it's
not terribly important. The budget's
more important, but the problem for for
the DNI is that
is that all but two of the intelligence
agencies that fall under the DNI are DoD
agencies, right? We're talking about
NSA, DIA, Army Intelligence, Navy
Intelligence, Air Force Intelligence,
Marine Corps Intelligence, DARPA, all
these different organizations that are
supposed to be intelligence services.
They're all actually just adjuncts of
the Pentagon. So, the Secretary of
Defense is in charge of them. That
leaves only the budget, which is secret
for ODNI. Now, the CIA director is
running operations, running analysis,
running R&D for science and technology,
um, briefing Congress and responding to
Congress. The CIA director is the one
that shepherds the CIA budget through
the uh, congressional oversight
committees. Even though DNI is supposed
to be on the flowchart higher than CIA
director, the CIA director is far more
important. Look at it this way, too. In
the last 50 years or so, about half of
the presidents have made the position of
CIA director a cabinet position.
DNI is not a cabinet position. It's
never been a cabinet position.
>> Isn't it now though?
>> It could be
on the whim of the president,
>> right? But isn't that um Tulsi Gabbard
is the one that is slated for that role,
right?
>> Correct. Yeah. But he hasn't said
whether whether she or Ratcliffe are
going to sit in on cabinet.
>> Oh,
>> in fact, I I don't think I'm almost
positive that CIA director was not a
cabinet position in Trump one and was
not a cabinet position under Biden,
but it was under
>> the benefit. Well, what is the what is
the difference? I mean, if you're going
to be a cabinet level or not. I mean,
one thing I could think is you don't
have to go through the Senate
confirmation hearing if you're not a
cabinet position.
>> Well, you do. Uh, C CIA director does
and DNI does, but CIA deputy director
does not.
>> Okay. So,
>> you know, and I'm glad you brought that
up.
>> Cabinet versus not. Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's just do you want this person
in on every decision or do you not want
this person in on every decision? Like
if if do you want the do you want the
CIA director sitting in a meeting to go
over your your you know housing
subsidization
policy really or whether or not you're
going to end the the the
uh Department of Education. It's kind of
a waste of time. And then, you know, for
all these years too, really since 19,
well, since the 1980s, um, the FBI
directors been jumping up and down and
saying, "Well, how come they get to be
in the cabinet and I can't be in the
cabinet?" Then you have that to deal
with, too.
>> Seriously, it's it's so pathetic.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, you're saying that the director of
the CIA is still more powerful than So,
John Ratcliffe will be more powerful
than Tulsi Gabbard in the new
administration?
>> By far. Yeah. By far. And you know, this
leads to another thing, too. Uh there
was a rumor in Washington just a couple
of weeks ago that Amorillis Fox Kennedy,
uh Bobby Kennedy's daughter-in-law and
and his campaign manager was going to be
named the deputy CIA director. And I
have to admit, I went on a couple of
shows and said I thought this was a
fantastic idea because she had been for
many years a deep cover CIA officer. She
knew how the organization worked from
the inside. But Senator Tom Cotton, the
conservative Republican from Arkansas,
said, "Oh, no you don't." Tom Cotton has
always wanted to be the CIA director. He
thought he was going to be CIA director
in Trump won. And uh Mike Pompeo was was
chosen instead. So So Cotton sent word
to the White House that he would block
Emorilus Fox Kennedy from being the CI
director. Well,
>> now the the word is that's okay. We're
going to make her the deputy national
security adviser. Well, the national
security adviser ranks above both the
CIA director and the director of
national intelligence. So, she's going
to be the deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism, which
makes her at least as important as the
CIA director.
trying to understand this flowchart.
It's
>> hard. A lot of the lines are dotted.
They're not straight.
>> Yeah. Well, and it it just seems like,
okay, you know, I would think my So, so
you're thinking that she's going to get
NSA or sorry, what was it?
>> NS
>> NSC deputy.
>> Oh, okay. And has that not been named?
That's deputy. So, who is the Is there a
secretary for that one? Is that a
cabinet position? No, it's it's a
cabinet position, but it is not subject
to congressional um confirmation because
it's an executive office of the
president position. So, that is uh
former congressman Walls of uh Florida,
three-term congressman, longtime member
of the of the intelligence committee.
Actually quite a very good choice.
Somebody who knows the way, you know,
the sausage is made.
>> Yeah. And I think she would compliment
him very well.
>> Okay.
>> She would be under him as the deputy.
Yeah.
>> You know, this leads to another thing
too.
>> Yeah.
>> I'm sorry to interrupt. John Brennan,
when he was the deputy national security
adviser for counterterrorism came up
with this thing called the kill list. So
every Tuesday morning at 9:00, a small
group of intelligence leaders would meet
and they would drop a list of everybody
who was to be killed that week with
drones. Um, I I'd be interested to know
if um if the Trump administration
continues that it's clearly a violation
of international law. None of these
people have ever been formally accused
of having committed any crime. Yet,
we're sending drones all over the world
to just murder them. If they're as bad
as we say they are, we should charge
them with a crime.
>> Um, we don't know if they're going to
continue that policy or not, but she
would be in charge of it.
Do you think um do you think and by the
way there's a lot of a lot of I think
criticism of Amarillis Fox uh Kennedy
because of somebody who's been in the CI
you know there's they look at her and
they say oh she was a CIA person so she
cannot be trusted. What do you say to
that? I mean you're you're a guy that a
lot of people trust. You were in the
CIA. I mean there's plenty of others who
were in the CIA but some will say once
in CIA you're never out. You know, once
a spook, always a spook. So,
>> I'm so glad I'm so glad you said that.
I'm I love when people ask me that
question because I I'm able to rant for
a minute. Um I said on Twitter the other
day, some somebody tweeted at me once
CIA, always CIA. And I responded that
that is the most intellectually lazy
statement that a person can possibly
make. Maybe I should call Ed Snowden and
Ray McGovern and Jeffrey Sterling and
you know half a dozen other people who
are the the family of Philip Agy and
say, "Oh, guess what guys, we're all
apparently still in the CIA." Um,
>> sure. There are a lot of people who have
been in the CIA who um are true
believers. I debated I debated a former
CIA officer recently, u uh Andrew
Bamante, who came off like he was doing
a two-hour long infomercial for the CIA.
So, sure, there are a lot of people like
that out there. She's not one of them.
She had a good career as a nonofficial
cover officer, deep cover, very hard
job, and very risky and dangerous. And
she just decided, I don't like the way
things work here. I'm leaving and she
left. So, she's seen the good, the bad,
and the ugly. And I I would consider her
to be more of an outsider now than than
the insider that she used to be.
Somebody who can make changes based on a
personal experience, changes that that
would be good for the country. Um, I
would take her over, you know, Tom
Cotton or or Mike Pompeo any day.
>> Yeah.
What do you think of the CIA? I mean, do
we need do we still do we need it? Do we
need the CIA?
>> No, I don't think so. There is so much
redundancy in intelligence. Well, I'm
going to give you a two-part answer.
First of all, there's so much redundancy
in in intelligence, we really don't need
a CIA. The Pentagon has an organization
called Defense Human Services. Hum
meaning human intelligence. They recruit
spies to steal secrets. Well, guess
what? That's exactly what the CIA does.
So, you've got DoD doing the same thing.
You've got the State Department's Bureau
of Intelligence and Research and the
Defense Department's Defense
Intelligence Agency doing um analysis,
exactly what the CIA's Directorate of
Intelligence does. So, there's
redundancy there. You have NSA that's
doing all of the the Intercepts. You've
got DARPA that's doing all the
futuristic cool scientific inventions
and stuff like that. You have myriad
organizations that are doing simpler
things like bugs or disguises or
forgeries or, you know, any of the stuff
that a CIA officer needs to do on a
day-to-day basis. So, when you've got
multiple organizations all doing exactly
the same thing, isn't that kind of a
waste of money and manpower? And
secondly, and this is more important,
the CIA has gotten literally every major
global development wrong since 1947.
from the creation of the Berlin Wall
through the Suez crisis, through the
Vietnam War and and the fall of the
Iranian government and and the loss of
the sha of Iran through, you know, Iran
Contra and missing 911 and everything in
between. They just got it wrong.
So why would we even want to keep going?
this gigantic multi-billion dollar
organization
that doesn't really provide anything to
the national security.
I worked for uh I worked for Ambassador
John Negropanti when I was at the United
Nations in New York uh more than 20
years ago. He later went on to become
the director of national intelligence
and as the ambassador to the UN, he was
in a quasi cabinet level position. And
so he was allowed to receive a PDB
briefing every day. And he once told me
that not one single time did the
president's daily brief tell him
something that the Washington Post and
the New York Times didn't tell him an
hour earlier.
Do we really need it?
>> Right.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It's so interesting. So
interesting. So So that's kind of an
Well, the the interesting I think the
most interesting part of what you just
said is I think a lot of people would be
cheering and saying, "All right, the CIA
is gone." Let's say Trump comes out and
says, "Ah, we're going to get rid of
this. We don't need it. We're going to
get rid of the CIA." People would be
cheering saying, "All right, you know,
it's a new day. It's a new dawn." And
really, it's like, no, they've just now
the the spies are everywhere else. They
just move his eyes around.
>> They just divide them up. Divide them up
and send them someplace else. That's it.
>> Yeah. So, it wouldn't actually end
anything. I mean, nothing would change
if we got rid of the CIA is what you're
saying.
>> You know, George Washington once said
that gentlemen do not read other
gentlemen's mail.
>> And so, we didn't have an intelligence
organization in our country until the
passage of the National Security Act of
1947. And even then it was almost
blocked because it was opposed by Jay
Edgar Hoover. It was only because
President Truman lied to Hoover and said
to Hoover, "No, no, you need to support
this passage because the CIA is going to
be a division of the FBI."
It was a clear lie, but Hoover believed
it and he said, "Oh, okay. Well, if I'm
going to be the director of both the FBI
and the CIA, then okay, I I'll lift my
objection." and it passed. And then
Truman was like, "Ha, fooled you." And
the CIA and the FBI have been at war
ever since.
>> Yeah. And what was the whole point of
the CIA? It was to spy on the Russians,
right? Is that what the initial
>> That's exactly right. It was to spy on
the Russians.
>> You know, Jim Jim Pavitt, he was the
deputy director for operations um for
whom I worked when I was a briefer. And
uh he used to say the same very simple
thing all the time and I repeat it all
the time now in interviews because it's
so true. The job of the CIA is to
recruit spies to steal secrets and to
analyze those secrets to provide the
policy maker with the best informed
analysis.
>> Now they often fail at that but that's
the whole reason at at its root to have
a CIA.
So the CIA, the the spies themselves are
not actual spies. They're recruiting
other spies in other countries to do the
spying. Is that
>> Yeah. You know, Yeah. We all have these
wonderful stories that we like to tell
once we leave about the cool stuff we've
done, but the truth of the matter is if
if you've got blonde hair and blue eyes,
you're not going to infiltrate al-Qaeda,
right? You're going to have to recruit
You're going to have to recruit some guy
from Yemen or from Egypt to do it for
you.
>> Yeah, that's that's really how it works.
You recruit the spies to steal the
secrets for you.
>> My favorite family member, he's passed
away now, but he was my great uncle and
uh my my grandmother's uh brother, and
he was in the CIA. He was one of the
very earliest first guys in the CIA. He
never said he wasn't, you know, we we
all we found out uh especially later
after he died, you know, then it was it
I think then it's like no longer it's
kind of like the family secret that's
not really that secret sort of a thing.
Like we all know Uncle Alton was in the
CIA kind of a thing, right?
>> And he would just disappear for weeks on
end and then come back with like random
Russian people.
>> Oh yeah.
>> You know. Oh yeah.
I mean, it's a little bit of an
exaggeration, but it was it was it was
like that. I mean, it was he would
disappear for weeks on end. And uh and
my grandma's like, "Oh, he's off Russia
again or something. The CIA, he's
involved in all that stuff." And
>> Oh, I can't tell you how many times
>> how many times I went on on missions and
I was instructed to throw away all of my
money before I left the country because
I couldn't risk anybody seeing like,
"Whoa, whoa, where you got money from
XYZ country? what were you doing there?
Uh, you can't risk that.
>> So, at the airport, just as I was
getting ready to, you know, board the
plane,
>> which was oftentimes in a fake passport
from some other country, so that there's
literally no record of me having been in
that country. I'd have to throw away all
my money and all my receipts.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow. Were you able to tell people you
were in the CIA when you were in it?
>> No.
>> So, what do you guys say? I mean, he
said his cover was always that he worked
for NASA. I think is what he said.
>> That's a good cover. I think he said
that's a good cover.
>> Yeah. He's like, I work in I work for
NASA. Yeah.
>> Mine was the State Department. I would
just say State Department. And uh if
people pressed, I would say, ah, it's
really boring. I'm involved in training.
That's what he would say sometimes.
>> Are you guys trained to say that?
Because that's literally what he would
say. It's really boring. I just do
paperwork. I
>> That's it. You want to make the response
Yeah. Yeah, you want to make the
response so boring that people don't
follow up. I'll tell you what, I was on
a plane once from Milan to Sophia,
Bulgaria. And I never talk to people on
planes. I just listen to music or read a
book or whatever. And I'm sitting next
to this this enormous guy and he would
not shut his mouth for the whole dog on
flight. And he kept talking and talking
and finally he says, "So, what do you do
for a living?" I said, "Uh, I I'm a
businessman." Oh, what kind of business
are you in? I said, 'I import export,
you know. Oh, what do you import and
export? Ah, whatever is going to make me
some money. I said, I whatever it is, I
can get a deal on. Oh, like what? He
says, and he just wouldn't stop. So, I
said, look,
I smuggle women and cigarettes from
Eastern Europe. You happy now?
>> And he says,
>> and that was actually true because
>> Yeah, right. It pretty much. No, it
wasn't true. I And he goes, "I don't
approve." I said, "Well, I didn't ask
your approval, did I? How about shut the
up?" And then he didn't say a word
the rest OF THE FLIGHT.
>> OH.
>> So sometimes that's what you have to do.
>> Now I know if somebody starts giving me
vague answers, I'll be like, "Ah, CIA.
Okay, got it."
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's right. Yeah. Training
and imports and and Yeah, we do a lot of
uh
>> Exactly. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Interesting. Interesting. But it
so yeah, I guess that's that's um
unfortunate to know that if we got rid
of it, it doesn't really go away. It
just shifts. It just it just morphs into
a different agency. I think that
>> that's right
>> because a lot of us want to see that
power, that kind of clandestine power.
Um we somehow we've got to bring the
power back to the people.
>> We've got to
>> Yeah. And it's
>> we've got to And you know how we do
that?
>> We we do that with with real oversight
committees. Here we've got the Senate
Select Committee on Intelligence and the
House Permanent Select Committee on
Intelligence, which for a brief period
from 1975
to about 1986 were actual real oversight
committees telling the CIA, "No, you
can't do that. That's a violation of
international law." And now the
committees really are are little more
than cheerleaders for the CIA. And I'll
give you an example. Um, I went to
prison for 23 months after blowing the
whistle on the CIA's torture program.
And when I got out of prison, I was
invited to a dinner at the Greek
ambassador's residence. And Senator Ron
Weiden of Oregon, the Democrat of Oregon
was at the dinner and um, and he came up
to me and he said, "Hey, welcome home.
So glad to hear that you're out. You
know, blah blah blah. You did this brave
thing." And I said, "Senator, with all
due respect, I got to tell you, I
actually expected a little bit more
support from you." And he got angry and
he said, "Look, it took all my energy
just to not lose my security clearance."
And I thought, "Oh, you're afraid of
them. You're not overseeing them. You're
afraid of them." Well, if he's the only
one on the Senate Intelligence Committee
who's viewed by the the media as, you
know, the one guy who's going to stand
up to the agency, what does that say
about all the other members of the
Senate Intelligence Committee, not to
even mention the House Intelligence
Committee? They're all cheerleaders. We
need real people. We need we need Daniel
Patrick Moyahan to come back to life or
Frank Church or Ted Kennedy who had the
guts to stand up to these guys and and
those those members of Congress just
don't exist anymore.
>> Do you have time to just tell us one
cool story from when you were in the CI,
you know, the story that you guys all
leave with?
>> Wow.
>> Tell us the story.
>> Well, you know what? I I will tell you
in advance. I've been very very
fortunate in recent weeks. I am going to
start in two weeks a 100 event one-year
speaking trip around the world. Um you
can more about it at
>> Yeah. Now what is this what does this
mean?
a speakers bureau in London has hired me
to to do 100 an evening with John
Kiryaku and I'm going to tell the these
kinds of stories and uh yeah I'm going
to do a hundred different venues over
365 days all around the world every
continent but Antarctica
and uh
>> wow that is going to be so cool you to
be able to travel like that and just
tell cool stories around a campfire
basically
I can't wait.
>> That's sort of that was so cool.
>> I've told this one story in particular
that it's funny. I never thought about
it being terribly, you know,
attentiongrabbing until I was told that
it was, but um I mentioned that I I
worked for the deputy director of the
CIA um as uh as his executive assistant.
It was it was the highest level job I
ever had in my life. And um my job was
to keep him briefed all day long on
events around the world. The events
being, you know, we're going to attack
Iraq in six months. And uh and the
director of the CIA, it was George
Tennant at the time. So the night before
we attacked Iraq, uh we had a secure
video teleconference called a civit
secure video teleconference in um George
and I were in the CIA's uh secure video
room and the meeting was chaired by the
vice president, Vice President Cheney.
Uh, Condisa Rice participated. Colin
Powell was there, the commander of
Sentcom, uh, the head of the NSA, the
national uh, I already said that uh, the
the, um, deputy secretary of state.
Anyway, it was about eight or nine, the
principles, the the top officers um, in
intelligence chaired by the vice
president. So, the vice president, Dick
Cheney, u starts off by asking um
General uh General Franks, Tommy Franks,
to give us something called the Order of
Battle. I always hated the Order of
Battle briefings because they're so
boring. I I would just like sit there
and he would say, "Well, he's got this
map of Iraq and uh he's got like we've
got elements of the first infantry uh
here and we have the 12th army corps is
there and elements of the third army
whatever they're moving here and moving
south and there are these arrows and it
never made any sense to me. This is what
DI DIA exists for. This is all they do.
So George is sitting at the head of the
table and um and I'm sitting directly
behind him taking notes and he's just
sitting there listening to the briefing.
And then General Frank says his exact
words, "If all goes as planned, we can
run by August."
And very calmly, George reaches forward,
turns off his microphone, and he turns
to me and says, "Did he say Thran or did
he say Baghdad?"
And I said, I said, he said Thran.
And he says, "Have these people lost
their minds?"
And then he turns back and he turns the
microphone back on and he just sits
there for the rest of the briefing. So
the briefing ends. I go back to the
deputy director's office and he says,
"How'd the briefing go?" And I said,
"Did you know we were going to invade
Iran?"
And he said, "Are they still talking
about that? We're not going to invade
Iran." He said, "These people know
nothing about the Middle East. They know
nothing about Middle Eastern history.
They think that they're going to throw
flowers at us when when we cross the
border. We're not going to invade Iran."
And we didn't because they didn't throw
flowers at us. No,
>> that's the White House.
>> Oh my gosh, that's the White House for
you, John. It's so great having you here
and talking. You You're just so
interesting. I'm so excited for you to
be able to go traveling. When do you
start that? When do you pack your bags
and get on the road?
>> Oh, yeah. I start in two weeks. So, my
first speech is going to be in Belfast
in on the uh 31st, and then I'm in
Dublin on the 1st, and then I'm in
I'm in Manchester on the 2nd. I'm going
to be back home for a few weeks, and
then I do 40 dates in the UK. So that's
England, Scotland, Wales, and um yeah,
and then off to Australia, New Zealand,
then Canada, then continental Europe,
the Persian Gulf, and Southeast Asia.
And then start the whole thing all over
again next year. It's It's going to be a
lot of fun.
>> That is going to be so great. All that
traveling and seeing and and eating all
the food. I'm so
Do you need an assistant? I'll go with
you.
>> I WOULD LOVE I'D LOVE to have an
assistant. I need a I need a conversant
because it's supposed to be an evening
with John Kuryaku. I need somebody to
sit next to me and say, "Hey, what about
>> I'll ask you questions."
>> Exactly.
>> May I add one other thing?
>> I can travel the world. That would be so
fun.
>> Why not?
>> All right. Tell us about how are you
doing that and this new TV show you've
got going on. How is that going on? So,
you've got a new TV show.
>> Yeah, I have a TV show that has been so
much fun. We've just we've just finished
our first season. It's on something
called Unified TV. It's unifyd
TV. It's It's uh online. You can go to
unified.com. And the show is called CIA
Declassified. So, we take original CIA
documents that have been declassified
and we use them to tell um stories of
these major international events that
have never been told before. We start
with the Berlin Wall. We go through
international assassinations and the
Kennedy murder and the Cuban missile
crisis and all different kinds of
things, the overthrow of the Iranian
government in 1953. Now, in season two,
we're going to bring outside experts in,
other CIA officers, for example, to talk
about these same issues and in some
cases to talk about their roles in these
issues. So, you can find all of it at uh
Unified TV. Again, it's unify
D and I'm also on Substack.
>> All right. Well, we do have the links
those links down below. Um, but very
cool, John. Thank you so much for being
here and
>> thank you, Kim. Such a pleasure about
all these subjects.
>> All right. Good to talk to you.
>> Thank you. Bye-bye.
>> Thank you for watching this clip from
the full Kim Iverson show, which you can
watch Monday through Friday, 5:00 p.m.
Eastern, 2:00 p.m. Pacific at kim
Iversonshow.com.
See you there.